Guide to the General Collection Manuscript Music Miscellany
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Delibes, Léo, 1836-1891
  - Music
    - Mélodies, 2. recueil. Faut-il chanter?
      - "L'oiseau m'a dit, faut-il chanter?", 1890 August 20; 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 27 x 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 40)
        Holograph score, with revisions, dated at Saint Nectaire.
        Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
    - Mélodies. 1. recueil. Heure du soir
      Song, with text by Armand Silvestre.
      - "Heure du soir / poésie d'Armand Silvestre", [circa 1863]; 1 ms. score ([5] l.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 70)
        Score, holograph, with printer's markings.
- Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929
  - Music
    - Copies of excerpts from Giovanni Paisiello's La serva padrona, 1916-1917; 2 ms. scores. (Box Folder 378)
      Transcription of a chorus, written in holograph by Diaghilev, signed, 1917 September 19, with annotation by him about the source in the Conservatorio di musica "S. Pietro a Majella" di Napoli; and transcription of an unidentified excerpt, copyist's manuscript with corrections, with annotation by Diaghilev about the source in the Accademia di Santa Cecilia, Rome, signed, 1916-1917, and other annotations by Diaghilev and Serge Lifar.
      Both scores have ownership stamps of Lifar.
      Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2003.
- Diémer, Louis, 1843-1919
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      - "Don Raphaël: opéra-comique en un acte / poême de Verconsin; musique de Louis Diémer", 1869-1870; 2 ms. scores ([circa 125] p.); 37 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 41)
        Full score and fragments of a vocal score, holograph with revisions, dated at Paris, 1870. Sections are signed and dated at Vichy and Lucerne, 1869 June-July, vocal score; and Lucerne, Paris, and Bex, 1869 August-September, full score. Accompanied by texts for two sections, manuscript in an unidentified hand.
- Dubois, Théodore, 1837-1924
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      - "Lecture, violon: concours, 1873 / Th. D.", 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 89)
        Music for solo violin and accompanying violin, score, autograph manuscript, signed at end, apparently for use in a competition or examination.
        Purchased from Bernard Quaritch (Sotheby's London sale, 2001 December 7, lot 59) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
- Duparc, Henri, 1848-1933
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, 1905 January 4; 1 item (2 p.). (Box Folder 419)
      Autograph letter, signed, to "cher Monsieur," a painter, about paintings by the recipient and giving news of Duparc's family.
      Purchased from Pierre Berès (Piasa sale, 2002 December 3, lot 67) on the Helen Hersh Torrence Fund, 2003.
    - Unidentified, undated; 1 item (2 p.). (Box Folder 420)
      Autograph letter, signed, to "cher ami," declining an invitation, with autograph music quotations from Richard Wagner, Siegfried, and Ludwig van Beethoven, Symphony no. 6, fifth movement.
      Purchased from Pierre Berès (Drouot sale, 2001 December 17, lot 51) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
  - Music
    - Aux étoiles
      Orchestra music.
      Originally the first part of Poème nocturne, composed 1874.
      Former group number: 18 DUPARC, HENRI
      - "Aux étoiles", [1874?]; 1 ms. score (12 p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 20)
        Score, with corrections, signed at end, and inscribed to Jean Cras and Francisco de Lacerda. A stamp of the publisher Rouart-Lerolle appears on the first page.
- East, Eleanor Mary
  - Music
    - "Songs and dances / Eleanor Mary East", 1796; 1 v. of ms. music ([circa 100] p.); 25 x 30 cm. (Box Volume 37)
      Manuscript music book containing songs for voice and keyboard and waltzes and other dances for keyboard. Some fingerings and dance instructions are present.
      Purchased from Justin Croft on the Robert W. Small Fund, 2009.
- Elman, Mischa, 1891-1967
  - Other Papers
    - Photograph of ME, n.d.; 1 photograph: b w; 25.4 x 20.4 cm. (Box Folder 228)
      Portrait photograph, signed and inscribed to an unidentified recipient, 1923 May 15.
      Former group number: 19 ELMAN, MISCHA
      From the collection of S. C. G. Watkins.
- Enesco, Georges, 1881-1955
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, 1920 Mar-Jul; 2 items. (Box Folder 229)
      ALS, 1920 Mar 3, to "Cher Monsieur," and ALS, 1920 Jul 13, to "Mon cher ami," regarding dates for rehearsals and concerts.
      Former group number: 20 ENESCO, GEORGES
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. (Sotheby's, London, 2000 Dec 8, lot 67on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
- Evreinow, Sergei Aleksandrovich, ca. 1895-1953
  - Correspondence
    - Green, Helen Marie, 1947 February 13; 1 item (1 p.). (Box Folder 421)
      Typed letter, about Aleksandr Nikolayevich Scriabin, with enclosed printed material about sound recordings of music by Scriabin published by Paraclete Music Disc, 1945 and undated, with manuscript and typescript annotations.
      Gift of Helen Marie Green, 2004.
- Falla, Manuel de, 1876-1946
  - Correspondence
    - Bautista, Julián, 1943 May 25; 1 item (1 p.); 27 cm. (Box Folder 230)
      TLS, Alta Gracia, Argentina, discussing Bautista's music.
      In Spanish.
      Former group number: 21 FALLA, MANUEL DE
      Purchased from John Wilson on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Jean-Aubry, Georges, 1910 Aug 21; 1 item (4 p.); 17 cm. (Box Folder 231)
      ALS, Paris, referring to poems of Jean-Aubry and performances of de Falla's music by Madame Gorska.
    - Jean-Aubry, Georges, 1919 [Dec 26?]; 1 item (postcard); 9 x 14 cm. (Box Folder 232)
      ALS, Madrid, to Jean-Aubry, London, informing Jean-Aubry of his departure for Paris, discussing concerts, and inquiring about accounts settled by the Ballets russes in London.
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. (Sotheby's, London, 2000 Dec 8, lot 67) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Jean-Aubry, Georges, 1929 Jul 12; 1 item (postcard); 9 x 14 cm. (Box Folder 234)
      ALS, Jean-Aubry, London, written on both sides of a postcard, to the editor of The Chesterian, concerning an article to be written by Falla.
    - Jean-Aubry, Georges, 1922 Sep 3; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 233)
      ALS, with address leaf, Granada, to Jean-Aubry, Saint Tropez, discussing an article to be written about Felipe Pedrell by Falla for the Revue Musicale and proposing another article about Pedrell for The Chesterian.
    - Roland-Manuel, 1925 Nov [17?]; 1 item (4 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 235)
      ALS, Granada, concerning an article written by Roland-Manuel about Falla and a manuscript by Emmanuel Chabrier given by Roland-Manuel to Falla.
- Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924
  - Correspondence
    - Nux, Paul de la, 1908-11, n.d.; 14 items. (Box Folder 238)
      Six ALS, with six envelopes, and eight postcards, holograph, signed, discussing his own work and that of others, including Massenet's Roma, and other musical matters..
      Former group number: 22 FAURE, GABRIEL
      Purchased from Autographe S. A. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Beaunier, André, 1912 Aug 27; 1 item (2 p.); 16 cm. (Box Folder 236)
      ALS, Lugano, Switzerland, to Beaunier, Seine-et-Oise, France, concerning Fauré's opera Pénélope.
      Date from postmark.
      Purchased from Galerie Arts et Autographes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Carré, Albert, 1920 Jan 6; 1 item (2 p.); 27 cm. (Box Folder 237)
      ALS, Monte Carlo, discussing his support of Robert Lortat as a successor to Louis Diémer at the Paris Conservatoire and congratulating Carré on a revival of La basoche, the opera comique by André Messager, with a libretto by Carré.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (3 p.); 18cm. (Box Folder 242)
      ALS to "Madame la Fée," referring to Catulle Mendes, possibly written during composition of his opera Penelope.
    - Unidentified, [1900]; 1 item (1 p.); 22 cm. (Box Folder 240)
      ALS to "Mon cher ami," discussing Dr. Jean Baratoux and standardization of pitch, appointment of Edouard Nadaud at the Conservatoire, and Fauré's relationship with "M. Réty".
      Date in an unidentified hand.
      Purchased from Clive Farahar & Sophie Dupre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1920, n.d.; 2 items. (Box Folder 241)
      ALS, Haute-Savoie, France, to "Chère amie," possibly Mrs. Johannes Wolff, 1920 Apr 11, inquiring about the English publisher Metzler; and brief ALS, undated, to an unidentified music engraver, concerning a proof.
    - Unidentified, [ca. 1880]; 1 item (1 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 239)
      Brief ALS to "Cher Monsieur," concerning a performance of Jules Massenet's opera La Vierge in Paris.
      Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
  - Music
    - Quintets, piano, strings, no. 2, op. 115, C minor
      Composed 1919-1921; first performed 1921; published 1921.
      - Fragment from Quintet for piano and strings, no. 2, op. 115, C minor, [ca. 1919]; 1 score fragment (2 p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 21)
        Fragment, with corrections, from the fourth movement, with a brief unidentified fragment on the verso.
    - Sonatas, violoncello, piano, no. 1, op. 109, D minor
      Composed 1917; first performed 1918; published 1918.
      - "Sonate pour piano et violoncelle, op. 109", 1917 Oct 25; 1 ms. score (33 p.) + 1 ms. part (8 p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 22)
        Engraved proof (Paris: Durand, c1917), corrected by Faure in holograph, with printer's markings, and printer's and publisher's stamps.
        Title from cover, in Faure's holograph.
        1ere epreuve; Epreuve corrige / Ch. Douin.
- Febvre, Frédéric-Alexandre, 1833-1916
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      Former group number: 23 FEBVRE, FREDERIC-ALEXANDRE
      - Music for piano, [ca. 1900]; 1 item (8 p. of music); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 23)
        Untitled music for piano solo, apparently in the hand of a copyist, with an inscription to Marie Kohn signed by Febvre.
        Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. (Sotheby's, 2001 May 25, lot 127) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
- Fétis, François-Joseph, 1784-1871
  - Correspondence
    - Van [Lamparen?], Monsieur, n.d.; 1 item (1 p.); 22 cm., mounted on sheet, 39 cm. (Box OVERSIZE FOLDER 24)
      Brief ALS requesting a transposition of trombone parts.
      Mounted on a leaf with notes about a letter from Thomas Attwood, which is not present.
      Former group number: 24 FETIS, FRANCOIS-JOSEPH
- Feydeau, Georges, 1862-1921
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (2 p.); 15 cm. (Box Folder 243)
      ALS asking the recipient to compose music for a ballet Feydeau is creating for the Folies Marigny.
      Former group number: 25 FEYDEAU, GEORGES
- Fitch, Nathaniel
  - Other Papers
    - Remarks on the science of music as it exists in the mind of man: New Haven, [18--]; 6 v.; 25 cm. and smaller. (Box Folder 244-248)
      Treatise, autograph manuscript, on music theory and composition, including musical examples. Most volumes are untitled; some contain different versions of the same material.
      Former group number: 26 FITCH, NATHANIEL
      Acquired 1898 Dec 1.
- Flotow, Friedrich von, 1812-1883
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, [1842?] Apr; 1 item (2 p.); 10 cm., mounted on sheet, 39 cm. (Box OVERSIZE FOLDER 24)
      Brief ALS to "Mon cher Monsieur," concerning performance of a song by Flotow.
      Date from annotation in an unidentified hand.
      Mounted on a leaf with letter from Etienne Nicolas Méhul (cataloged separately). English translations of letters, for which originals are not present, from Adolphe Adam to "Regnier," undated, and from Hector Berlioz to an unidentified recipient, undated, are on verso.
      Former group number: 27 FLOTOW, FRIEDRICH VON
- Gascoigne, Edward
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      Former group number: 27 GASCOIGNE, EDWARD
      - Vocal and instrumental music, 1764 Dec 18; 1 v. (77 p.) (Box Volume 12)
        Bound autograph manuscript of instrumental and vocal music, including folk tunes, love songs, hymns, in English and other languagues.
        Source unknown; found in stacks, 1935.
- Giordano, Umberto, 1867-1948
  - Music
    - Marina. Vocal score
      Opera, with a libretto by Enrico Golisciani.
      Composed while Giordano was a student at the Naples Conservatory; sixth place in the Sonzogno Competition, 1899.
      Former group number: 28 GIORDANO, UMBERTO
      - "Marina: melodramma in un atto / di Umberto Giordano", [ca. 1889]; 1 ms. vocal score ([126] p.); 31 cm. (Box Volume 13)
        Vocal score, with corrections and revisions.
        Four pages containing earlier drafts, formerly pasted over, precede pages 16 and 20 and follow pages 17 and 19.
    - Mese Mariano. Vocal score
      Opera, with a libretto by Salvatore Di Giacomo.
      First performed 1910.
      - "Mese Mariano", [ca. 1910]; 1 ms. vocal score ([159] p.) (in a case); 35 cm. (Box Volume 14)
        Vocal score, draft with revisions. Parts of the libretto, in Di Giacomo's holograph and typescript, are affixed to some facing pages. Includes annotations by a former owner concerning comparison to a published version and identifying the score as part of the estate of Giordano's widow, Olga Spatz-Wurms.
        Sections are paged separately; continuous page numbers added by a former owner.
        Bound by a former owner.
        Purchased at Christie's, London, (lot 96) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
- Glazunov, Aleksandr Konstantinovich, 1865-1936
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, undated; 1 item (1 p.) (Box Folder 379)
      Autograph letter, signed, to "Cher Monsieur," about the recipient's piano reduction of a symphony by Aleksandr Porfirevich Borodin.
      Purchased from Julian Browning on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
    - Unidentified, 1929 October 21; 1 item (3 p.) (Box Folder 380)
      Autograph letter, signed, Paris, to "Nikolai Andreevich," concerning a tribute for M. P. Beliaev twenty-five years after his death, and other subjects In Russian.
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002.
  - Music
    - Unidentified
      - Unidentified music, 1911 February 9; [3] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. and smaller. (Box Folder 381)
        Sketches, holograph, signed and inscribed to Vasilii Il'ich Safonov; and three exercises, holograph, signed, written for a dinner following a concert by Safonov.
        Annotations in Russian.
  - Other Papers
    - Photograph of AKG, undated; 1 item (Box Folder 382)
      Portrait photograph, inscribed to "Ivan Grigor'evich," 1916. Inscription in Russian.
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002l
- Gounod, Charles, 1818-1893
  - Correspondence
    - Adam, Juliette, 1880 May 20; 1 item (1 p.); 16 cm. (Box Folder 249)
      Brief ALS to Adam (Juliette Lamber), declining an invitation.
      Former group number: 29 GOUNOD, CHARLES
    - Auber, Daniel François Esprit, 1856 Jul 13; 1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 25)
      ALS, Paris, thanking Auber for appointment to a Conservatoire jury for "Concours d'orgue, de Contrepoint, de Fugue, et de Grand opéra."
    - Déroulède, Paul, 1875 May 2; 1 item (3 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 250)
      ALS discussing his military song En avant!, with words by Déroulède, and an invitation for "vendredi juin 6" [i.e. Friday Jun 4?].
      Purchased from Pierre Berès on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Halévy, Fromental, Madame, [1864 spring]; 1 item (2 p.); 22 cm. (Box Folder 251)
      ALS to the widow of his former teacher, written near the premiere of his opera Mireille, discussing Fromental Halévy.
    - Marchesi, Salvatore, 1878 Oct 22; 1 item (2 p.); 14 cm. (Box Folder 252)
      ALS, with envelope, St. Cloud, discussing a Viennese production of Philémon et Baucis and the premiere of Polyeucte in October, 1878.
    - Unidentified, 1878 Mar 11; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 257)
      ALS to "Chère charmante amie".
      Purchased from Charavay on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1871 Mar 16; 1 item (1 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 254)
      ALS to "Dear Sir," concerning corrections to an unidentified work.
    - Unidentified, 1874 Mar 27; 1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 256)
      ALS to "Chère Madame," discussing painter Ernest Hebert.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (2 p.); 14 cm., mounted on sheet, 39 cm. (Box OVERSIZE FOLDER 24)
      ALS to "Monsieur," concerning Gounod's health and thanking the recipient for his concern.
      Mounted on a leaf with letter from F. Halévy. English translation of a letter, for which the original is not present, from Ludwig van Beethoven to "Herr Holz" undated, is on verso.
    - Unidentified, 1868 [Jul?]; 1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 253)
      ALS, Morainville, to "Cher ami," concerning ballet music for his opera Faust.
      Dated "Lundi, 19 [juillet?], 1868."
      Purchased from David J. Holmes (Swann sale, 1999 Oct 14, lot 65) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1873 Feb 6; 1 item (1 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 255)
      ALS, London, to "Monsieur," inquiring how Gounod may obtain sonatas composed by the recipient.
      Purchased from David J. Holmes (Swann sale, 1999 Oct 14, lot 64) on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
  - Music
    - Ange gardien
      Choral music (4 equal voices), with text by A. Quételard.
      Composed 1858; later published for solo voice and piano.
      - "L'ange gardien: choeur à 4 voix egales / paroles de Quételard; musique de Ch. Gounod", [1858]; 1 ms. score ([6] p.); 18 x 27 cm. (Box Folder 386)
        Score, holograph.
        Dedication on cover: "Aux petits enfants."
        Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2000.
    - Chanson de printemps
      Song, with text by Eugène Tourneux.
      Published in 1860.
      - "Le chant du printemps", 1849; 1 ms. score ([3] p.) + 1 ms. part ([1] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 46)
        Score, holograph, signed on cover, with a separate vocal part for verses 2-3.
    - Cinq Mars
      Opera, with libretto by Paul Poirson and Louis Gallet, after Alfred de Vigny.
      Composed 1876-1877; first performed 1877; vocal score published 1877.
      - Fragments from Cinq Mars, [circa 1876-1877]; 3 ms. score fragments ([23] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 42)
        Fragments, holograph, from "La fête chez Marion Delorme," vocal score, and from the end of act I and an unidentified section, full score.
        Purchased from Pierre Berès on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004.
    - Crépuscule
      Song, with text by an unidentified author.
      Composed 1866.
      - Crépuscule, [circa 1866]; 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 82)
        Score, holograph, with words in an unidentified hand.
        Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Library Associates Endowment Fund, 2003.
    - Deux reines. Hotellerie de la reine
      Opera, with libretto by Ernest Legouvé.
      Composed 1864; first performed 1872; vocal score published 1873.
      - "L'hotellerie de la reine: introduction (choeur et couplets)", [circa 1872]; [4] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 53)
        Chorus part for bass I, holograph.
        Purchased from L'autographe on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1998.
    - Dodelinette; arr.
      Originally for piano, 4 hands.
      Published 1872.
      - "Dodelinette: berceuse pour les instruments à cordes / Ch. Gounod", 1876 April 14; 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 50)
        Score for an arrangement for string orchestra, holograph, dated at Paris.
        Dedication on cover: "à ma fille, Jeanne Gounod."
        Purchased from Pierre Berès on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2000.
    - Gallia; arr.
      Motet for soprano, chorus (SATB), orchestra, and organ, with text from the Lamentations of Jeremiah.
      Commissioned by the organizing committee of the London International Exposition for the opening of the Royal Albert Hall, 1871 May 1; composed while Gounod was living in London during the Franco-Prussian War.
      Arranged by Georges Bizet for voice, piano, organ, and violin or violoncello, and for piano, four hands, 1872.
      - "Gallia: lamentation: pour voix, piano, orgue, violon ou violoncelle / paroles et musique de Ch. Gounod", [ca. 1872]; 1 ms. score (21 p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 26)
        Engraved proof with holograph corrections by Bizet. Accompanied by the published score, two parts for soprano or tenor, with words in French, Italian, Latin, and German, and parts for organ-harmonium, violin, and violoncello (Paris: Choudens, [1872]). The proof, score, and parts are signed by Mme. Jules Barbier, wife of the playwright and librettist.
        Caption title. "Gallia" is printed, with remaining title information written in manuscript. Edition statement in manuscript.
        Pl. no.: A. C. 2280.
        N. 2. édition pour soprano.
        Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Edith and Richard French Fund.
    - Masses, A major
      - "Messe (no. I) en lab à trois voix: avec accompagnement d'orgue / Ch. Gounod", 1844; [36] p. of ms. music; 31 cm. (Box Folder 258)
        Organ part, with blank staves for voices, signed by Gounod on cover and initialed by him on several pages. The cover is annotated in an unidentified hand: "Propriété de la paroisse de St. François-Xavier, maître de chapelle Joseph Franck".
        Gounod was appointed maître de chapelle at the Séminaire des Missions Etrangères, Paris, in 1843.
        Jean-Hubert-Joseph Franck, violinist, composer, and organist; younger brother of César Franck; succeeded Gounod as organist at the Séminaire des Missions Etrangères.
        Purchased from Jean-Jacques Faure on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Polyeucte. Invocation à Vesta
      Opera, with libretto by Jules Barbier and Michel Carré, after Pierre Corneille.
      Composed 1869-1878; first performed 1878 October 7; published in vocal score, 1878.
      - "Récit et invocation à Vesta: fragment de Polyeucte", 1878 April 2; 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 48)
        Score, holograph, signed at end.
        Pages numbered 125-128.
        Purchased from Lisa Cox on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
    - Près du fleuve étranger
      For chorus (SATTBB) and orchestra, with text by A. Quételard, after Psalm CXXXVII.
      Composed 1861.
      - Fragment from Près du fleuve étranger, [1861]; 1 ms. score fragment ([3] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 55)
        Score fragment, holograph.
        Inscribed to A. Quételard, with reference to another fragment given to the publisher Lebeau.
        Accompanied by a printed score (Paris: Lebeau, undated), inscribed by Quételard to "Monsieur l'Abbé Ibos, Alger," 1878 November 2.
    - Rédemption. Ténèbres; arr.
      Rédemption, an oratorio with libretto by Gounod, was published in 1882, vocal score, and 1883, full score.
      - "Ténèbres", [1880s?]; 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 45)
        Score for an arrangement for piano, 4 hands, holograph, with corrections, signed at end.
    - Réponse de Medjé
      Song, with text by Marie Barbier.
      Published in 1882.
      - "Tu m'aimes!: réponse de Medjé / paroles de Marie Barbier; musique de Ch. Gounod", [circa 1882?]; 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 47)
        Score, holograph, with revisions, signed at end. Piano part is incomplete.
        Purchased from Les Autographes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
    - Sapho
      Opera, with libretto by Emile Augier.
      Composed 1850-1851; first performed 1851; revised 1858 and 1883; vocal score published 1860.
      - Fragments from Sapho, [circa 1851?]; 2 ms. score fragments ([15] p.); 37 cm. and smaller. (Box Oversize Folder 54)